<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King a proclamation for the new making, altering, amending, dressing, repairing, proouing, and stamping of armours, gunnes, pikes, and bandaliers, both of the common armes, and armes of the trayned band throughout England and Wales.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22542</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33150482</idno>
  <idno type="VID">28629</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240904420</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 8977</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S3570</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22542)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28629)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1876:137)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King a proclamation for the new making, altering, amending, dressing, repairing, proouing, and stamping of armours, gunnes, pikes, and bandaliers, both of the common armes, and armes of the trayned band throughout England and Wales.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6] leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie: and by the Assignes of Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXXI [1631]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The London Company of Workmen-Armourers to oversee all army and county weapons.</note>
                  <note>"Giuen at Our Court at Greenwich, The thirtieth day of Iune, in the seuenth yeere of Our Reigne."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Worshipful Company of Armourers and Brasiers in the City of London.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Armor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Weapons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:28629:1"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>❧ By the King.</signed>
            </opener>
            <head>❧ A proclamation for the new making, altering, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending, dressing, repairing, proouing, and stamping of Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, and Bandaliers, both of the common Armes, and Armes of the I rayned Band throughout <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas Wee foreseeing in Our Princely Iudgement how</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary it is for the preseruation of Our Selfe, and the Subiects of Our Kingdome in generall, That the Armors, Gunnes, Pikes, and Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daliers within this Realme, be from time to time repayred, amended, dressed, and stamped: And that those Armes according to the iust and full number charged by the Muster-Rolles in euery seuerall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, bee fully furnished, and compleatly maintayned, which now as wee are credibly informed are in many parts of this Kingdome much decayed and neglected, and that expert and skilfull workemen may bee trayned vp, imployed, and maintayned, as well in times of Peace, as of warre: To the end we may not bee enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in times of warre to seeke for Armes, Armours, gunnes, Pikes, and Bandaliers in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne parts, and so bee eigher vnprouided of them, or supplied at deare and vncertaine Rates, at the pleasure of Forreigne Princes or States, when any vnexpected occasion of imployment, or sudden Seruice for the safety and honour of Our Person and State shall require.</p>
            <p>And wee well weighing in Our Princely consideration the dangerous consequence thereof, did for Our better Information, referre the further consideration thereof to Our Councell at warre and other speciall Committees, who vpon mature deliberation haue certified Vs, That the Company of Workemen Armourers, Gunne-makers, Pike makers, and Bandalier-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Our Citie of <hi>London</hi> (being the skilfullest and prime workemen of this Land) are most fit to bee empployed and encouraged in this Seruice; That so they hauing conuenient employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in time of Peace, Wee may be assured of their true and effectuall Seruice in the times of Warre, and yet they to performe the said Seruice at such Rates and Prices, as shall not bee left
<pb facs="tcp:28629:2"/>to their own discretion, but shalbe particularly agreed vpon and ordered; And thereupon We haue by and with the aduice of Our said Councel of War, and by and with the aduice of the Lords and others of Our Priuie Councel, granted a Commission vnder Our great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> vnto <hi>Iohn Francklin, William Crouch, Iohn Ashton, Thomas Steeuens, Rowland Foster, Nicholas Marshall, William Coxe, Edward Anesley,</hi> Workemen Armourers, <hi>Henry Rowland, Richard Berrowe, Thomas Addis, Iohn Norcot, William Dawstin, William Watson, Iohn Watson,</hi> and <hi>William Graues</hi> Gun-makers; <hi>Iohn Edwards, Robert Tacker,</hi> and <hi>Bartholomew Ray</hi> Pike makers, and <hi>Iohn Gace,</hi> and <hi>William Beauchamp,</hi> Bandalier-makers, Freemen of Our Citie of <hi>London,</hi> Workmen of those Trades or Mysteries, who are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly willing to vndertake this Seruice, and haue according to the said Certificate, giuen cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Our Office of Ordinance, to be ready when we shall haue occasion to set them on worke moneys, fifteene hundred Armours, euery Moneth: And the Gun-makers as many Muskets, and bastard Muskets, and small shot vpon the same warning; As also the Pike-makers and Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalier-makers a proportionable number vpon like warning, for Our Seruice: And that they the said Armourers, Gunne-makers, Pike makers, and Bandalier-makers will bring vp Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices from time to time, to be expert and skilfull in these seuerall Occupations, which are so necessary for the defence of this Kingdome, so as they may bee employed in making, mending, dressing, stamping, and repayring of Armonrs, Gunnes, Pike and Bandaliers in the Citie and Countrey; And haue agreed and entred Bond as aforesaid, that they will not exceed the Rates and Prices in a Schedule to the said Commission annexed, &amp; mentioned, expressing the seuerall Rates and Prices, which shall bee allowed them respectiuely for the said worke, which are very reasonable, and not onely without grieuance, but very much for the ease and benefit of Our Subiects, who are or shall bee concerned, in respect of their former trouble and charges in that kind, and likewise will performe such other directions, as wee shall from time to time prescribe vnto them for the better aduancing of so publique and necessary a seruice, as need shall require.</p>
            <p>And that Wee and Our Kingdome may thus bee supplied with so necessary and vsefull a Seruice, Wee did by Our said Commission giue vnto them, their Deputies, Assistants and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes, and euery of them, by them or the greater part of them lawfully authorised, free libertie, licence, power and authoritie to trauell, or goe into any County, place or places within this Our Realme of <hi>England,</hi> and the Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> aswell within Liberties as without, as there with the approbation and assistance of the Lord Lieutenant and deputie Lieutenants, where they should happen to come, or of any other to bee by them deputed and appointed, to make a diligent Suruey of all Armes, Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, and Bandaliers whatsoeuer, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be found and maintained at the common Charge of any Citie, Towne or Village, and of the Trained bands, in euery Countie, aswell horse as Foot throughout Our said Realme of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales;</hi> And vpon, and after the said Suruey to new make, alter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, dresse, repaire, proue, and stampe (as need shall require) all or any the said Armours, Guns, Pikes, and Bandaliers, and make them complete and fit for Seruice, as by the said Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and deputy Lieutenants, or any other by them deputed or appointed as aforesaid, should be be approued and directed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28629:3"/>
            <p> And that by the direction of the said Lord Lieutenants, or their Deputy Leutenants of the seuerall Counties, and Diuisions respectiuely, the said Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, and Bandaliers once or twice a yeere, or oftener (if need shoud bee) bee brought to such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient place, and places vpon the Muster dayes, or at such other conuenient time, and times as they should thinke fit, to the end the same might be then and there viewed and suruayed, and as occasion should require, bee altered, amended, or renewed, as aforesaid, and that they might the better performe this Our seruice, and informe Vs by the Lord Lieutenants, and Deputy Lieutenants, as aforesaid, as occasion should require of all such defects, and negligences, as might happen from time to time, wee haue by the said Commission giuen vnto them, their Deputies, and Assignes, full power and authority, by the direction of the said Lords Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, or Deputy Lieutenants, as aforesaid (if they shall so thinke of it fit, and behoouefull for Our Seruice) to require all Ministers of Musters, who haue the Records, or keeping of the Muster-rolles of the said Armours, foorthwith to deliuer vnto our said Commissioners true Copies of the said Muster rolles, to the end they might bee truely enformed who ought to be charged with the sayd Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, and Bandaliers according to the iust num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and natures of them.</p>
            <p>And vpon the same suruey to obserue what numbers of Armes, Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, and Bandaliers were wholly wanting, as aforesaid, that are appointed and ought to bee charged vpon any person, or persons, in any place, and to distinguish the vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruiceable from such as by mending, and repaying, might bee made seruiceable, and to set downe the numbers and natures of the defects, and to make vp the said Suruay in a Booke, vnder the hands of Our said Commissioners, or any one, two, three or more of them, to bee signed, and approoued of by the Lord Lieutenant, or Deputy Lieutenants, or such as they in euery place shall depute for that purpose, to assist in the said Suruay: And likewise vpon such their Suruay to approoue of all such Armes, of the Common Armes and Trayned Band as should bee found fit for seruice, and to prooue and try all sorts of Gunnes, Pikes, and Bandaliers of the said Common Armes, and Trayned Band before they bee vsed, or exercised, and to approoue of such as should bee seruiceable for warres, at the Owners charge, and being prooued, should allow as fit for seruice, and allowing should Stampe the same with the <hi>A.</hi> and the <hi>Crowne,</hi> being the Hall Marke of the Company of workemen Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourers of <hi>London,</hi> which Marke or Stampe shall (with the consent of the Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or his Deputy Lieutenants) remaine in their custody who shall haue the charge to bee entrusted with the execution of this Seruice: wherein, and in Our said whole Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are futher to follow such Iustructions as are, or shall bee giuen foorth from Vs, or the Lords of Our Priuie Councell, or Councell of warre in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>And to the end no abuse, or deceit might bee in the number of Armes, Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, or Bandaliers borrowed one of another, wee did by the said Commission, giue Our said Commissioners, or the <hi>Maior</hi> part of them, their Deputies, or Assignes, power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to cause to bee framed, and made, and to vse, two other Markes or Stampes, to be first allowed by the Lords Lieutenants, or Deputy Lieutenants, or such as they should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
<pb facs="tcp:28629:4"/>for that purpose, the one to distinguish the County, the other the place or Diuision, where the said Armes, Armours, Gunnes, Pikes or Bandaliers are charged and bee; which Markes or Stamps shall remaine in the custodie of Our said Commissioners, or some of them their Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or Assignes, and shall be entred into the said Booke of Suruay, to be Signed as abouesaid, for vsing and putting to of which Markes and Stamps of the place or Diuision aforesaid, wee did by Our said Commission hold it fit that Our Lord Lieutenants, or Our Deputy Lieutenants in euery place and Diuision should appoint and set downe some competent allowance vnto Our said Commissioners, their Deputies or Assignes for their labour and attemdance vpon Our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice herein.</p>
            <p>And that vpon the entreatie of Our said Commissioners, their Deputies or Assignes (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the wants and defects of the said Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, and Bandiliers, should ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vpon the said Booke of Suruay signed as aforesaid, Our said Lords Lieutenants and their Deputy Lieutenants of the seuerall Counties respectiuely in Our name should command and giue order to the seuerall places and persons chargeable therewith, within a reasonable time, and at some conuenient place, to be prescribed to supply such defects, either by prouiding new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours Gunnes, Pikes and Bandiliers, or by mending and repayring the old, as there should be cause.</p>
            <p>And to the end no excesse of Prices may either through necessitie or ignorance bee put vpon the Countrey for new Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, or Bandiliers; or for the dressing, repayring, prouing and stamping the old and seruiceable, wee did by Our Commission require and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, That no Armourer, Gun-maker, Pike-maker, or Bandalier-maker, who should bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in this Seruice, should demand, take or receiue for any new Armours, Gunnes, Pikes or Bandaliers, for dressing, repayring, proouing or stamping the old, or any part of them aboue the rates and prices in the aforesaid Schedule expressed.</p>
            <p>And wee did also by Our said Commission, will, require and command, all persons charged with Armes, Armours, Gunnes, Pikes or Bandaliers of the common Armes, or the Trayned Band, that should then after haue of Our said Commissioners, their Deputies or Assignes any new Armours, Guns, Pikes or Bandaliers, or should haue any Armours Guns, Pikes or Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daliers, dressed, amended, repayred, proued or stamped by them or any of them, That they vpon such hauing or receiuing from them any such new Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, or Bandaliers; or vpon their hauing of their Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, or Bandaliers, or any of them dressed, amended, altered, repayred, proued, or stamped, as aforesaid; should satisfie, content and pay Our said Commissioners, their Deputies or Assignes, or any of them for the same, according to the Rates &amp; Prices in the foresaid Schedule expressed and set down: And if any difference at any time should arise touching the natures or numbers of defects, betweene the Armourers, Gun-makers, Pike-makers and Bandalier-makers imployed for the said new making, mending, dressing, repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, prouing and stamping of any of the Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, or Bandaliers, of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Armes or Trayned Band aforesaid, and those in whole custody the said Armours, Gunnes, Pikes or Bandaliers should be or remaine, That the same should be ordered by the Lords Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, or Deputie Lieutenants, or any of them, or such as should be by them or any one of them deputed for the time being, who should take the Suruey about mentioned, as by Our said
<pb facs="tcp:28629:5"/>Commission amongst diuers prohibitions, and other things therein contained, more at large it doth and may appeare.</p>
            <p>Now to the end all Our louing Subiects may take knowledge what wee command ro forbid to be done in this so important and necessary Seruice for the generall good of this Our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and that Our people may not plead ignorance, wee doe hereby will, require and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all and singular Our Lieutenants, deputy Lieutenants, Iustices of Peace, Maiors, She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes, Muster-masters, Captaines of Bands, and their Lieutenants, high Constables, Consta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Headboroughes, and other Our Officers, Ministers, and louing Subiects, That they and euery of them be from time to time aiding, helping, and assisting vnto Our said Commissioners, their Deputies, Assistants, and Assignes, and to such others, as shall bee by them, or any of them employed in the execution of the same Our Commission or the Seruice thereby required and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in all things, as shall be most meet, and to performe what to them or any of them respec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely shal appertaine according to Our pleasure herein, and by Our said Commission declared.</p>
            <p>And because wee are credibly giuen to vnderstand, that the often and continuall altering and changing of the fashion of Armes and Armours (some Countreys and parts of this Kingdome hauing Armours of one fashion, some of another) doe put many of Our louing Subiects to a great and vnnecessary charge and more then need requireth: For the auoding whereof, Our will and pleasure is, And we doe hereby appoint and command, That hereafter there shalbe but one vniforme fashion of Armours of the said common and Trained Bands throughout Our said Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> when as any of the said Armours shall be supplied and new made, And that, that forme and fashion of Armour shall be agreeable to the last and moderne fashion lately set downe and appointed to be vsed by the Lords and others of Our Councell at warre. The paternes whereof are now and shall remaine in the Office of Our Ordinance from time to time; which is Our pleasure likewise concerning Gunnes, Pikes, and Bandaliers: whereof Paternes are and shall remaine from time to time in Our said Office.</p>
            <p>And Our will and pleasure also is, That (for the better completing of euery of the Musketiers of Our said trained Band, and that they may be better fitted and appointed for Seruice (if need require) euery Musketier of the common and Trained Band, shall haue, and bee from time to time furnished and prouided of an head piece, agreeable to the moderne fashion of the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces of the Footmans Armour, whereof the paterne remaineth also in Our foresaid Office of Ordinance.</p>
            <p>And whereas we are likewise credibly informed, That diuers Linkers, Cutlers and Smiths, and other Botchers of Armes, by their vnskilfulnesse haue utterly spoiled many Armes, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Gunnes (which by a skilfull workeman might haue beene altered, dressed, amended, and made seruiceable) and yet haue required great rates of the Countrey for doing thereof, and diuers Tradesmen of other Trades and Mysteries, doe buy, barter and sell Armes, Armous, Gunnes, Pikes and Bandaliers, which are bad and insufficient, to the great preiudice of Our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Subiects, the same also not being agreeable to the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme.</p>
            <p>Wee doe therefore hereby straightly charge and command, prohibite and absolutely forbid, That no person or persons whatsoeuer (not hauing serued seuen yeeres, or beene brought vp as an Appreutice or Apprentices in the Trade or Mystery of an Armourer, Gunn-maker, Pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, and Bandalier-maker, and thereat serued their time of seuen yeeres (other then the
<pb facs="tcp:28629:6"/>said Commisioners, their Assignes, Deputies, Factors, or seruants, or such as they shall allow of, and employ, and shall bee bound to doe Vs such Seruice, when they shall bee thereunto requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and haue his Name and dwelling place entered by Our said Commissioners, or some of them by their recommendation, in the Office of Our Ordinance, as aforesaid) doe make, mend, alter, change, dresse, repaire, prooue, or stampe any Armes, Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, or Bandaliers of the Common Armes, or Trayned Band whatsoeuer, or any others, or any of them, or any part of them, or intermeddle therein.</p>
            <p>Neuerthelesse, it is Our will and Pleasure, And we doe hereby straightly charge, Command, and declare, That Our said Commissioners giue encouragement, and respect, vnto all such Skilfull and well-deseruing workemen, of all sorts of Armes as they shall finde in euery place, or part, within this Our Kingdome, and Dominion aforesaid, to haue them employed, and set on worke.</p>
            <p>And it is Our will and Pleasure, That if Our said Commissioners shall not bee present, either by themselues, their seruants, deputies, or assignes in euery County and place, when, and where any defects in Armes, Gunnes, Pikes, and Bandaliers at Musters or other such publike meetings in each County shall bee found: Or if Our said Commissioners, or any from, or vnder them, beeing so present in any County, and Place, shall bee vnwilling, and negligent to make, amend, dresse, repaire, and stampe the said Armes, Gunnes, Pikes, and Bandaliers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the intent to Our said Commission, and these presents.</p>
            <p>Then it shall be lawfull in such their negligence, and default, at such time, or times, and in such cases onely for the said Owners of Armes to carry their Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, and Bande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers vnto such Countrey workeman beeing skilfull in their Trade, as heretofore haue made, or amended any of them, to amend, and repaire them as heretofore they haue done, without any trouble, or interruption of Our said Commissioners, or any for, or vnder them, Any thing in these presents, or in Our said Commission to the contrary, notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And wee doe hereby also absolutely forbid, That no <hi>Ironmonger, Cutler, Chaundler</hi> or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sou whatsoeuer, doe from hencefoorth Went, or Sell any Armes, Armours, Gunnes, Pikes, or Bandaliers, or any part of them, but such as shall bee prooued, and stamped with the said Hall Marke of the Company of workemen Armourers aforesaid, beeing the proofe Marke, and also warranted by Our said Commisioners, or some of them, or such as they shall appoint thereunto, and be allowed by them to be sufficient, vpon paine and penalty of Our high indignation, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure, and such other penalties, and imprisionments, as by the Lawes of this Realme, or by Our Prerogatiue Royall may be inflicted vpon them, for such their Offences and contempts.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Our Court at Greenwich, <date>The thirtieth day of Iune, in the seuenth yeere of Our Reigne.</date>
               </dateline> God saue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent MAIESTIE: and by the Assignes of Iohn Bill, M.DC.XXXI.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>